Donovan, Hope; Papers apap168
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Hope Donovan Papers1970-2003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Donovan, Hope, 1970-2003
apap168
3 cubic ft.
This collection consists of a variety of materials collected by Hope Donovan during her work as an environmental activist and prominent member of the League of Women Voters of New York State. Most of the collection consists of publications, reports, conference proceedings, guides, and papers from such subject as Adirondack Park, development issues, and the Smart Growth Conferences.
Biographical History
Hope Taussig Donovan was born on August 29, 1923 in St. Louis, Missouri. Donovan attended Washington University in St. Louis. She was involved substantially with the League of Women Voters (LWV), serving on its New York State Board and working for the Albany County chapter of the organization. Donovan had a long-term interest in environmental issues and was noted for her efforts in passing the New York State Bottle Bill, which included a well-publicized walk from Buffalo to Albany to raise awareness of the issues. She worked as a lobbyist for the LWV at the state level, frequently supporting environmental issues. In addition, she was a Legislative Representative for the Adirondack Mountain Club from 1986 to 1990.
Water and air quality were central among Donovan's environmental interests and she was a member of Albany County's Water Quality Coordinating Committee. In 1986, she gave testimony before the U.S. Senate Committee on Environment and Public Works about acid rain issues. Donovan, a Guilderland resident, died on August 26, 2003. At the time, she was survived by husband Robert A. Donovan, a professor in the Department of English at the University at Albany.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of a variety of materials collected by Hope Donovan during her work as an environmental activist and prominent member of the League of Women Voters of New York State. The collection spans the years 1970 to 2003. The vast majority of the materials are concerned with environmental issues in New York State. The most prominent single subject is water resources, particularly watersheds and groundwater. Other prominent subjects are the Adirondack Park, development issues, and the Smart Growth Conferences from 1999 to 2001. Materials of note include a folder on New York State's Bottle Bill, in which Donovan played a crucial role, and materials related to Guilderland (where Donovan resided), including town history, planning, and land use.
Most of the collection consists of publications, reports, conference proceedings, guides, and papers. There are also some memos and correspondence. Original signatures are rather infrequent, however. Most of the material was not written by Donovan herself, although it does include scattered handwritten notes. It is almost entirely concerned with the various environmental and civic activities connected to Donovan's career, rather than with her personal papers. Generally, the only materials that diverge from the kind of formats mentioned earlier are several maps and plans, related to the Adirondack Park in particular, and a film entitled "A Salute to Garbage."
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged in two series: Water Resources and Subject Files.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Charles Rielly in November 2003. 2003 November
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Conservation and the Environment; Adirondack Park (N.Y.); League of Women Voters of New York State; Adirondack Park Agency (N.Y.); Files by subject; Annual reports; Donovan, Hope
- Water Resources, 1979-2002; 1; 1.0 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists primarily of material about watersheds and groundwater in New York State. It contains numerous reports prepared by New York State government agencies, particularly the Department of Environmental Conservation, the Department of Health, and their units. This series also contains other studies, newsletters, correspondence, and various photocopied material relating to water resources in New York. A significant amount of material is connected to planning issues.
  - The 1996 Priority Waterbodies List (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 1)
  - Great Lakes Commission, 1987-1990 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 2)
  - Groundwater Conference, 1993-1995 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 3)
  - Groundwater Conference, 1993-1995 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 4)
  - New York State Source Water Assessment Program Plan, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 5)
  - Nonpoint Education for Municipal Officials, Reports and Guides, 1996-2000 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 6)
  - Nonpoint Source Management Program, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 7)
  - Organic Chemical and Drinking Water, 1979 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 8)
  - Source Water Assessment Program Plan, Draft, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 9)
  - Watershed, 1998-2001 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 10)
  - Watershed, League of Women Voters, 1984-2000 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 11)
  - Watershed, League of Women Voters, 1984-2000 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 12)
  - Watershed, New York State Government, 1996-2002 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 13)
  - Watershed Planning Handbook for the Control of Nonpoint Source Pollution, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 14)
  - Watersheds in New York, Reports and Guides, 1995-1998 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 15)
  - Where to Find Information on Nonpoint Source Pollution in New York State, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Water Resources), Folder 16)
- Subject Files, 1970-2003; 2; 2.0 cubic ft.
  - 2020 Vision: Fulfilling the Promise of the Adirondack Park, Reports, 1988-1990 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - 2. Adirondack Council, Reports, 1986-1988 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Adirondack Park Agency, 1981-1989 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Adirondack Park Agency, Citizens Guides, 1980-1986 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Adirondack Park, Maps and Plans, 1980-1988 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Adirondack Park, Publications, 1970-1990 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Adirondack Park, Reports and Ephemera, 1988-1990 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - The Albany Pine Bush Preserve Commission, Brochure and Pamphlet, 2000-2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Bottle Bill, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Coastal Management Conference, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Coastal Management Project / Citizen Education Project, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Coastal Zone Management Program, Report and Appendix a-e, 1976-1977 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Coastal Zone Management Program, Report Appendix f-i, 1976-1977 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Conservationist, 1985 May-June (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Conserving Open Space, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Conserving Open Space in New York State, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - The Department of Environmental Conservation: A 25th Anniversary Review, Executive Summary, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Division of Lands and Forests, 1986 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Empire State Forest Products Association, New York Forest Policy Summary, 1987 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Energy, Government, Consumer, Nuclear Waste, 1980-1989 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Finding Common Ground: Conserving the Northern Forest, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - The First New York State Environmental Congress, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Funding Land Resource Acquisition, Recreation Facility Development and Stewardship in New York State The Next Step, Report, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Growing Together within the Capital Region and Capital District Population & Household Projections, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Guilderland, Environmental Resources and Planning, 1989-2000 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Guilderland Hamlet Neighborhood Association, By-laws, Minutes, Town History, 2002- 2003 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Hazardous Waste Information: Focus on New York State, 1986 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Hudson River Valley Greenway, 1989-1999 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - League of Women Voters, Reports and Guides, 1975-1997 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - A Look at Our Town, Village, City, County Government, 1982 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Making Land Use Decisions, 1975 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - New York State Canal System, 1993-1994 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - New York State Canal System, Public Hearing, 1991-1992 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Natural Resources Current Focus, Bumper Sticker, 1978 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Oregon, Department of Land Conservation and Development, 1992-1995 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Smart Growth Conference, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Smart Growth Conference, 2000 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Smart Growth Conference, 2001 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Smart Growth Conference Proceedings, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Smart Growth Conference Proceedings, 2000-2001 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Smart Growth Working Group, 2001 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Soil Interpretation Report: Pine Bush and Surrounding Area, 1974 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - State and Local Governments Partnering for a Better New York, 2001 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - A Salute to Garbage, Undated (Reel 1)